-==www.RagBear.com==-
是, 首相  第1季第8集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译: vivitata
校对: tpring
时间轴: T-boy
我们的人
你好啊 亲爱的
Hello, darling!
啊 是新闻 讲到我了吗?
Ah, the news! Got to me yet?
没有 你又干什么了?
No. What have you done now?
好激烈的质询 他们攻击
A sensational Question Time. People were attacking
我控制军费的计划
me about my controlling defence expenditure
被我驳了个落花流水
I really made mincemeat of them.
新闻还没提呢
They haven't mentioned it yet.
典型BBC作风      这不是BBC
Typical BBC.        It's not BBC.
典型ITV(独立台)作风      这是4频道
Typical ITV.       It's Channel 4.
那还能指望什么?
Well, what can you expect?
快完了      开大点声
It has only several minutes to go.        Turn it up, then.
对本琪命运的担忧日益增长
There's growing anxiety for the fate of Benji,
这条老英国牧羊犬
an 0ld English sheepdog,
昨夜穿过铁丝网
who last night got under the wire
闯入索尔兹伯里平原炮兵靶场
and into the artillery range on Salisbury Plain.
本琪的主人是8岁女童琳达弗莱彻
Benji belongs to 8-year-old Linda Fletcher.
琳达去年在车祸中失去了双亲
Linda lost both her parents in a car crash.
只有本吉和她活了下来
Both she and Benji survived.
不幸的是 该区域遍布着未爆弹
Unfortunately, the area is full of unexploded shells
险象环生 只有一条安全道路
and is highly dangerous except for one fixed road.
本琪距该路甚远 似已迷路
Benji is a long way from the road and seems to be lost.
军方深表遗憾
The Army expressed their regrets,
但同时表示 除非它回到道路上
but say that unless he comes to the road
否则他们无能为力
otherwise there's nothing they can do.
若无意外 它将很快饿死或被炸死
If nothing happens soon he will either starve or be blown up
琳达决心
Linda is preparing to
在靶场外再守一夜
spend another night's vigil on Salisbury Plain,
盼望本琪归来
hoping that Benji will come back.
晚间新闻播送完了
And that's the news this evening.
你肯定从头看到尾了吗?      肯定
Are you sure you watched all of the news?        Yes.
真的一点都没提我?
Was it on, the bit about me?
没有 除非我看漏了
No. Unless I missed it of course
你说你看全了的
You said you watched it all.
可你知道 人总会自动无视无聊的部分嘛
But one mentally tunes out the boring bits.
不是说你 亲爱的 你不无聊
Not you, dear. You're not boring.
至少对我不会 就算全国人民都这么想
Not to me,even if you are to the rest of the country.
亲爱的 英国国防大计正在
The future defence of Britain was being
全民论坛上引发激辩
fought out in the great forum of the nation
结果观众看到什么?
and what do they give the viewers?
真人版"灵犬莱希"
A rerun of ''Lassie Come Home''!
我觉得军方应该出面救狗
I think the Army ought to rescue that dog.
每天都有孩子丢狗
Kids lose dogs every day.
军队救得过来吗?
Should the Army rescue every one of them?
你不懂平头百姓的心
You don't understand ordinary people feel.
我正是一名平头百姓
I happen to be an ordinary person myself.
不会吧      你要我浪费纳税人的钱
Oh, surely not        You want me to waste taxpayers' money
收买便宜人心?
on buying a bit of cheap popularity?
有时候你非得做些经济上不合算的事
Sometimes you have to do things
这就是文明社会
that aren't economic in a civilised society.
写成报告提交财政部啊
Write a paper on that and submit it to the Treasury.
内阁经济委员会
We don't get many laughs
正愁没笑话听呢
in the cabinet of economic communitee
军情五处处长来了 首相
The Director General of MI5, Prime Minister.
你好 杰弗里 快进来
Ah, hello, Geoffrey. Come along in.
谢谢 首相
Thank you, Prime Minister.
请问能不能...
Eh, I wonder if...
没关系 我的会晤伯纳都在场 对吧伯纳?
Oh, that's all right. I always have Bernard present.
这次不行 首相
Not this time, Prime Minister.
啊 我也不一定要伯纳在场的 对吧
Ah. I don't always have Bernard present.
请坐 我没收到这次会晤的文件
Do sit down. I don't have any papers for this meeting.
是没有 太严重了      怎么?
No, it's too serious.        Why?
我们刚收到一些情报
We've just received some information.
你们不就干这个的吗?
Isn't that what you're supposed to do?
您知道约翰霍斯特吗?
Do you know John Halsted?
你前任 60年代军情五处首脑 上个月死了
Your predecessor.The header of MI5 in '60s. Died last month.
他把全部私人文件留给了我们
He left his personal papers to us.
我们刚开始审查
We've started to go through them.
显然他五六十年代传过政府情报给莫斯科
It`s very clear he was passing government secrets to Moscow
传了好几年
several years in the '50s and '60s.
军情五处首脑? 是俄国间谍?
The head of MI5? A Russian agent?
似乎是这样
So it seems.
他干嘛留文件给你们?
Why did he leave his papers to you?
遗嘱上说是临终良心发现
His will said it was a final act of conscience.
我觉得是想死后出风头
I think it's just posthumous gloating.
炫耀他没被抓住
Showing us he could get away with it.
他泄露出去多少?      这倒无所谓
How much did he tell them?        That hardly matters.
有了剑桥五人组和
I mean, with Burgess, McLean, Philby, Blake
克罗格夫妇(波特兰间谍网 1961)
and Fuchs and the Krogers,
再多一个也没什么不同
one more didn't make much more difference.
重点在于 他是我们的人      我们的人?
The point is he was one of us.        One of us?
剑桥毕业直接入军情五处
Joined MI5 straight from Cambridge,
一辈子做公务员
Being in the Civil Service all his life.
一旦传出去
If this ever gets out,
他任内招募的人永远洗不清了
all of us recruited in his time will be suspects for ever.
对啊...你该不是间谍吧?
Yes. ..You're not a spy, are you?
开玩笑的 你真不是吧? 算了
Only joking. You're not, are you? No...
不仅如此
This is not all.
我们对约翰爵士发起过
We held an internal security investigation
内部安全调查 在70年代
into Sir John in the '70s.
媒体闹得满城风雨 记得吗?      好像有
There was a lot of speculation. Remember?        Vaguely.
完全不负责任 空穴来风
All totally irresponsible and ill-informed.
媒体指控他是间谍的事?      对
When the press suggested he was a spy?        Yes.
他确实是啊      对 可他们又不知道
Well, he was.        But they didn't know that!
他们一点不了解情况
They were being totally ignorant.
也不负责 歪打正着罢了
They are not responsible. They just happened to be accurate.
总之 那次调查把他完全洗清了
Anyway, the inquiry cleared him completely,
可他们忽略了些很明显的疑问和检查
but they missed some rather obvious questions and checks.
所以显然...人们有所怀疑
So obvious that...well... One wonders.
对
Yes.
人们怀疑什么?
What does one wonder?
人们怀疑那些洗清他的家伙
One wonders about the chaps who cleared him.
对啊 他们会不会太蠢 是吗?
I see. Whether they were stupid, you mean?
不 首相 他们会不会也是...
No, Prime Minister. Whether they were also...
间谍? 天啊
Spies?! My God!
谁主持的调查?
Who headed that inquiry?
老麦维爵士 可他当时身患重病
Old Lord MacIver, but he was ill a lot.
好吧 其实是老糊涂了
Well, ga-ga, actually.
所以实际上 是他秘书在主持
So, effectively, it was the secretary who conducted it.
秘书是谁?      汉弗莱阿普比
Who was the secretary?        Humphrey Appleby.
汉弗莱?      正是 首相
Humphrey?        Yes, Prime Minister.
你觉得他可能也是间谍?
You think he may have been a spy, too?
有这个可能性 不过微乎其微
It's a remote possibility, but very unlikely.
他总归是我们的人      约翰霍斯顿也是
After all he's one of us.        So was John Halsted.
这倒是 不过没有别的证据对汉弗莱不利
Well, yes, but there's no other evidence against Humphrey.
他会不会掩护了某个我们的人...
Might he have been covering up for one of us...
他们的人...你们的人?
one of them...one of you?
大概是吧 可我毫不怀疑他的忠诚
I suppose so, but I have no doubts at all about his loyalty.
更有可能他仅仅是...
It's much more likely to be just...
严重失职
Hideous incompetence.
我们还没审完文件
We haven't been through the rest of his papers.
您可以先对汉弗莱爵士发起调查
You could hold an inquiry into Sir Humphrey.
我可以吗?     虽然在这个阶段我不推荐
Could I?        Well, I wouldn't recommend it at this stage.
消息可能泄露 不能再掀起不负责的媒体疑云了
We don't want more irresponsible speculation.
就算是正确的      尤其是正确的
Even if it's accurate.        Especially if it's accurate.
最可怕的莫过于正确
There's nothing worse than accurate,
不负责 空穴来风的媒体疑云了
irresponsible, ill-informed press speculation.
您可以给汉弗莱放园艺假
You could send Humphrey off on gardening leave
等我们审完霍斯顿文件
while we examine the rest of the Halsted papers.
园艺假?
Gardening leave?
当然 然后您可以跟他当面对质
Certainly. And you could confront him.
潜在证据全在这了
The substantive evidence is all here.
要是他没什么嫌疑
Look. If you don't really suspect him.
我们不能当没这回事吗?
Shouldn't we just forget about it?
很显然 这取决于您
Well, obviously, it's your decision,
可如果您不管
but on the other hand if you did nothing and it emerged later
今后爆出来汉弗莱爵士真是...
that Sir Humphrey...that he was...
他们的人 那可就不太好看了
..one of them, well, it might not look too good.
更不用说作为内阁秘书
Not to mention that as Cabinet Secretary
他也协调我们所有安全事宜
he co-ordinates our security services.
什么也瞒不过他      有道理
There are no secrets from him.        You're right.
可我真不敢相信
But I find it hard enough to believe
一个我们的人 是个他们的人
that one of us was one of them.
可如果两个我们的人 都是个他们的人
But if two of us were one of them...
两个他们的人
Two of them.
我们所有人就可能是...
..all of us could be, um...
他们所有人
All of them.
谢谢 杰弗里 我听够了
Thank you, Geoffrey. I've heard enough.
岂有此理 我们支持率又降3个点
Awful! Another three points down in the polls.
政府没有 只是您个人的支持率
Not the government. Only your personal rating.
我犯了什么错?
What have I done wrong?
低支持率通常表示您做得对
Low popularity usually means doing things right.
不是因为我没削减军费吧?
It's not my failure to get defence cuts?
老实说 首相 我觉得军费算不上
To be honest, I don't think defence cuts are the
今天全国坊间热门话题
principal topic of conversation in supermarkets.
不是军费 那是什么?
What is it if is not my defence policy?
依大众媒体来看
To judge from the popular press,
恐怕是索尔兹伯里平原上走丢的狗
I am afraid it's the lost dog on Salisbury Plain.
也许政府需要个丢狗政策
Perhaps the government needs a lost dog policy.
还有事吗 首相?
Is there anything else, Prime Minister?
对 还有一件事
Yes, there is something else.
安全的事 伯纳 你不介意吧?
A security matter. Bernard, would you mind?
什么?
I'm sorry?
你干什么 伯纳?      我以为...
What are you doing?        Well, I thought...
没有人 就是...
There wasn't anyone...that he's
我是希望你回避一下
I was just hoping you'd leave us alone.
但我没有...哦 好吧
But I haven't...Oh. Yes.
首相      对了 汉弗莱
Prime Minister.        Yes, Humphrey.
有件事我得跟你谈谈
There's something I want to talk to you about.
一件...重要机密
Something...very secret.
如果我也回避会好说些吗?
Would it be easier if I wasn't here?
几年前 有一桩安全调查
A few years ago, there was a security inquiry.
你记得约翰霍斯顿爵士的名字吗?
Does the name Sir John Halsted ring a bell?
当然记得 实际上
Yes, of course. In fact,
调查正是我本人主持的
I had to conduct the inquiry myself, virtually.
你没查到什么疑点吗?      当然没有
And you found nothing incriminating?        Of course not.
首先 约翰霍斯顿是我们的人
In the first place John Halsted was one of us.
是我多年老友了
We'd been friends for years.
其次 整件事都是媒体炒作出来的
In the second place The whole story was got up by the press
第三 内部安全调查的宗旨
and in the third place the whole object of internal security
就在于查不出证据
inquiries is to find no evidence.
就算领土安全受到威胁?
Even if the security of the realm is at risk?
首相 如果您真觉得
Prime Minister If you really believe the security of
有威胁 该找政治保安处
the realm is at risk, you call in the Special Branch.
政府安全调查只是
Government security inquiries are only
消灭媒体谣言用的
used for killing press stories.
使得首相能在下院里宣布
They enable the PM to stand up in the House and say,
"经全面调查"
"We held a fully inquiry"
"这些指控毫无证据"
"and there is no evidence to substantiate these charges."
如果真查到疑点呢?
What if you have found something suspicious?
首相 其实政府中一切都可疑
Practically everything happened in government is suspicious.
您支走伯纳 私下跟我谈
The fact that you asked Bernard to leave us alone
这就堪称可疑
for a secret conversation might be construed as suspicious.
没错      不过总之 那件事纯属无稽之谈
Indeed.        But the whole story was clearly a nonsense.
典型舰队街(英国报界)的煽风点火
Typical Fleet Street sensationalism.
那么约翰爵士不可能给俄国传了情报?
So he wasn't passing secrets to Moscow?
不可能 没有的事
Impossible. Out of the question.
你敢以名誉担保?      毫无疑问
You'd stake your reputation on it?        Without hesitation
这样啊 好吧 很遗憾告诉你
I see. Well, I'm afraid I have to tell you
在他任内大半时间
that for a substantial part of his career
他都是个俄国间谍
he was a Russian spy.
我不相信 谁说的?
I don't believe it. Who says so?
他自己 他留了所有文件给政府
He does. He left his papers to the government,
包括一份详细自白书 军情五处已经证实了
including a detailed confession. MI5 agrees.
从头至尾核对无误
It checks out all along the line.
可是...
But...
天啊 他...我说 他是...
Good Lord, he... I mean, he was...
我们的人?
One of us?
正是 这会留下很多问题啊
Exactly This certainly leaves a lot of questions to be asked
对 我先问你
Yes, and I'm asking you the first of them
为什么没向他提很多问题?
why didn't you ask him a lot of questions?
为什么调查那么快就洗清了他?
Why did the inquiry exonerate him so quickly?
我告诉您了 而且 我们当时很忙 再说...
I've already told you! Anyway, we were very busy. Besides...
天啊 您不会觉得...
Good Lord! You don't think...?
当然 不会有人怀疑...
I mean, surely nobody suspects...?
我还能怎么办?
What else was I expected to do?
你应该进行充分调查
You could have held a proper inquiry.
你有证据证明
After all you had evidenced
他有次停在南斯拉夫 时间长得出奇
a surprisingly long stay in Yugoslavia.
所以呢?
Yes?
不久 几个军情五处探员被捕了
Shortly afterwards, several MI5 agents behind the archon
从此再没露面
were rounded up and never seen again.
对...      他老是和一个翻译泡在一起
Yes...        He spent a lot of time with one interpreter.
那翻译是个俄国间谍 对 我们知道
And she turned out to be a Russian agent.Yes.We knew that.
大多数南斯拉夫翻译是俄国间谍
Most Yugoslav interpreters are Russian agents.
如果不是中情局间谍的话
Those who aren't with the CIA, that is.
你根本没追查
You never followed it up.
我事情多得很
I had better things to do with my time.
三个月后 她搬来英国
Three months later, she moved to England and
在剑桥定居
settled in Cambridge,
离约翰爵士家130米
150 yards from Sir John Halsted's house.
后来他们做了11年邻居
They were neighbours for the next 11 years.
唉呀
Crikey!
总不能什么都查吧
You can't check up on everything!
没准会查出什么来呢
You never know what you might find!
如果您真有所怀疑 就应该...
If you have such a suspicious mind. You ought to...
发起安全调查
Hold security inquiries.
对...不
Ye...no!
约翰霍斯顿向我保证过 一位绅士的保证
John gave me his word. Halsted. The word of a gentleman.
随便吧 汉弗莱 我有个问题了
Anyway, I have a problem.
问题?      就是你
A problem?        You.
我? 您该不会认为...
Me? You don't think...?
您不可能认为...
You couldn't think...
我一句俄语都不会说啊
I don't speak a word of Russian!
可想而知 要么是失职 要么是串通
It must be either incompetence or collusion.
串通? 我向您保证 首相 绝无串通
Collusion? I give you my word it wasn't collusion!
绅士的保证?      没错 牛津的绅士
The word of a gentleman?        Exactly! An Oxford gentleman
家里花园怎样?      哦 这个...
How's the garden?        Oh, well, it...
首相 我求您 别给我园艺假
Prime Minister. I beseech you, not gardening leave.
为什么?
Why not?
我得保持名誉啊
I have my reputation to think of!
你拿它担保霍斯顿的清白了
You've already staked that on Halsted's innocence.
总之 汉弗莱 我还得考虑
Anyway. Humphrey. I have a lot of thinking to do.
我得跟你的前任谈谈
I think I'll talk to your predecessor.
阿诺德? 为什么?
Arnold? Why?
我对这种事没经验
I've no experience of this sort of thing.
我得请教阿诺德
I have to ask Arnold's advice on
怎么对内阁秘书搞安全调查
setting up a security inquiry on a Cabinet Secretary.
总之 谢谢你 汉弗莱
Anyway, thank you, Humphrey.
没别的事了
That will be all.
好吧...
Yes...
暂时没事了
For the time being.
别跟阿诺德商量 等我先找他
Don't discuss this with Arnold until I've spoken to him.
当然不会 首相 我怎么会是那种人
Of course not, Prime Minister! I wouldn't dream of it.
那你建议我怎么办 阿诺德?
So what do you think I should do, Arnold?
难说
Difficult.
部分取决于你到底是不是间谍
Depends a bit on whether you actually were spying or not.
阿诺德      人总不能有偏见嘛
Arnold!        One must keep an open mind.
可我不可能是 我又没上过剑桥
But I couldn't have been. I wasn't at Cambridge.
我不是他们的人 我有家室
I'm not one of them. I'm a married man.
我是我们的人 当了一辈子公务员了
One of us. I've been in the Civil Service all my life.
约翰霍斯顿也是      对 可他不一样
So had John Halsted.        Yes. But he was different.
怎么?      约翰当年抱有什么信仰 理想
Why?        Well, John used to believe in things. Causes.
我这一生从没有过任何信仰
I've never believed in anything in my life!
他还有想法 独创的想法
He had ideas. Original ideas.
你知道我跟那种事从不沾边
You know I've never done anything like that.
反正 就算你是间谍 我也同意不能捅出去
Anyway. Even if you were spy, I agree it mustn't get out.
真的 阿诺德?
Do you, Arnold?
当然 把信息透给俄国确实很严重
Of course. Giving information to Moscow is serious.
把信息透给任何人都很严重
Giving information to anyone is serious.
比如内阁
The Cabinet.
但这种丑闻 会重创公务员系统威信
But a scandal like this could gravely weaken
所以你绝不能认罪
the authority of the service. You mustn't confess.
可我没罪可认啊
But I haven't done anything to confess to!
就算如此 还有另一种可能
Be that as it may, there is still the other possibility.
为了讨论方便 我们先假设你是无辜的
Let us assume,for the sake of argument,that you are innocent
谢谢 阿诺德      只是假设 绝不含偏见
Oh, thank you, Arnold       Just assuming, without prejudice
那就得考虑失职问题了
Then the question of incompetence arises
可我没失职
But I wasn't incompetent.
是你安排我做调查组秘书
You made me the secretary to the House did the inquiry
你当时明白交待
You made it clear
不能查出对他不利的证据
that we were expected to find no evidence against him.
我可不记得
I have no recollections of that.
你心里一清二楚
Oh! You know perfectly well.
你有书面证据吗?      当然没有
You have written evidence of this?       No. Of course not.
那我们接着说你的失职问题
So we return to the question of your incompetence.
你我也许知道
You and I may know
你只是做了份内的事
that you did the job you were required to do,
可这对政客很难解释
but it's hard to explain that to politicians.
非得告诉他们吗?
Do they have to know?
当然 我们尽量避免 危险在于首相
Not if we can help it. The PM is the danger.
他也许会散布出去      那怎么行
He may want to go around to tell people.        He mustn't!
你能制止他吗?      我不知道
Can you stop him?        I don't know.
你必须制止他 要是他告诉内阁呢?
You have to stop him. Suppose he told the Cabinet?
要是内阁把你停职呢?
Suppose they decided to suspend you?
调你去做战争公墓委员会主席呢?
Remove you to the chairmanship of the War Graves Commission
他们无权这样     他们有权 但他们不能
They couldn't!        They could, but they mustn't.
不是因为你 你是可以牺牲的
But not because of you. You are expendable.
我不是
I'm not!
一旦树立起原则
Once they accept the principle that
资深公务员可以因失职被罢免
senior civil servants can be removed for incompetence,
这可是导火索
that would be thin end of the wedge.
我们会失去几十名同事 甚至几百名
We could lose dozens of our chaps. Hundreds, perhaps!
几千吧 阿诺德 我该怎么办?
Thousands. Arnold, what am I going to do?
我建议你提升你对首相的重要性
I suggest you make yourself so valuable to the PM
就趁未来几天
over the next few days
让他不能够放你走
that he cannot afford to let you go.
怎么做?      他目前最愁什么?
How?        What is he really dead set on at the moment?
支持率
Popularity.
亲爱的汉弗莱
My dear Humphrey
所有政客都愁这个
That is what all politicians are dead set on
可他在近期调查中有所下滑
But he's dropping at the moment in the polls.
那你得把他推上去
Then you must lift him up again.
让他在时下头条新闻中大出风头
Give him a popular role in the biggest current news story.
时下头条新闻是
Well, the biggest current news story is
平原上走失的一条狗
a lost dog on Salisbury Plain.
所以呢?      阿诺德
Well?        Oh, Arnold.
你建议我让首相在
Are you suggesting that I have the Prime Minister
索尔兹伯里平原爬来爬去
crawling all over Salisbury Plain
一手拿探雷器
with a mine detector in one hand and
一手拿袋狗粮?
a packet of Winalot in the other?
大概对英国来说
It would probably do Britain less harm
这是他会做的事之中最无害的
than anything else he'd be likely to be doing.
国防部常任秘书到了
The Permanent Secretary for Defence.
诺曼 谢谢你过来
Norman, good of you to come.
我的国务大臣在内阁干得怎样?
How did my Secretary of State do in Cabinet?
凑合吧 我想内阁开始
Well, so-so. I think Cabinet is starting
怨恨他拒不削减军费的立场了
to resent his refusal to make defence cuts.
可他毫不松口      对
But he didn't back down?        No.
很好 找我什么事?
Excellent. What can I do for you?
有个敏感问题
Well, it's rather a sensitive one.
巡航导弹?      不是
Cruise missiles?        No.
星战计划(反弹道导弹系统)?      不是
Star Wars?        No.
那是什么?
What, then?
是索尔兹伯里平原上那条狗
It's this dog on Salisbury Plain.
那个啊 首相抱怨了?
Oh, that! The PM getting his knickers in a twist?
别担心 一切都在掌控之中
Don't worry. It's all under control.
是吗?      没错 本周末保证饿死
Oh, really?        It will starve to death by the weekend.
然后他们会捡回尸体 埋葬在靶场大门口
They'll recover the body and bury it just outside the gates.
卫兵枪口朝下致哀
Guards resting at arms reversed.
司令安慰泪汪汪的小女孩
The C.O. comforting the weeping little girl.
电视台全面报道
Telly will lap it up,
周日报纸刊发动人的图片 毫无问题
We'll get lovely pictures in the Sundays. No problem.
救它怎么样?
How about rescuing it?
别傻了 汉弗莱 很危险的
Don't be silly, Humphrey. It's dangerous.
用安全方法救      安全方法?
But to do it safely.       Safely?
你是说一支皇家工兵中队手持探雷器
A squadron of Royal Engineers with mine detectors,
一队兽医手持麻醉枪
the Veterinary Corps with stun darts,
一架带一两台绞车的直升机
a helicopter with winching equipment possibly two
一张高达几十万的账单
and a bill up in the hundreds of thousands
就为一条狗 在任何宠物店5块钱就能买到
for a dog you could replace for a five at the local pet shop
但理论上可行?
But it could be done technically ?
理论上什么都可行 有钱的话
Anything can be done technically, if you've got the money.
你能安排吗?
Could you do it?
你疯了吧
You must be mad!
首相正在步步紧逼 要我们削减开支
Here we are under the greatest pressure to cut spending
你建议我们浪费几十万
and you suggest that we waste hundreds of thousands
当着全世界媒体救一条狗
in front of the press on a dog!
这是要我们部门自取灭亡
It would be departmental suicide.
对 可如果有首相授权
Yes, but if the Prime Minister were to authorise it,
如果是他发起的
if it was his initiative,
不就使他更难坚持
wouldn't it make it harder for him to
削减国防经费了吗?
insist on defence cuts after that?
汉弗莱 你果真才智过人
Humphrey, you excel yourself.
尤其要瞒着他真实成本
Especially if he didn't find out the true size of
营救结束再汇报
the cost until after the rescue.
你要我怎么做?
What do you want me to do?
做好营救准备 严加保密
Put the rescue operation on standby in strict confidence.
并保证一切功劳归于首相
And promise me the PM will get all the credit.
绝不允许你们国务大臣
No nonsense about your Secretary of State
沾光蹭人气 这是10号的事
trying to muscle in on all the publicity.An NO.10 job
军情五处向你汇报了?
You've been briefed by MI5?
是的 首相 真不幸
Indeed, Prime Minister. Unfortunate.
简直是灾难啊
Disastrous. I said.
当然不算灾难 绝不会捅出去的
Not disastrous. Surely It will never come out.
事情被大家发现了才算灾难吗?
You mean things are only disastrous if people find out?
当然
Of course.
就算内阁秘书是间谍这种事?
Even if the Cabinet Secretary is a spy?
可我很高兴告诉您 没这回事
I'm happy to say that is not the case.
你怎么能肯定?
Why so sure?
军情五处刚在霍斯顿文件里找到这个
MI5 have just come across this in the Halsted papers,
他的私人日记
from his private diary.
"又一次会见了那个头号呆瓜阿普比"
"Another session with that prize goof Appleby.
"耍得他团团转"
''Fooled him completely."
"他没提半个棘手的问题"
"He never asked any difficult questions."
"似乎连军情五处报告都没看"
''didn't seem to have read the MI5 report."
"他脑子那么迟钝"
''So much wool in his head"
"糊弄他纯属小菜一碟"
"it's child's play to pull it over his eyes.''
这绝对...      洗清了汉弗莱爵士
That certainly...        Exonerates Sir Humphrey.
阿诺德 我真没法形容我有多开心
Arnold...I can't tell you how happy this makes me.
要不要...      不不 我留着
Shall I...?        No, no. I'll keep this.
就是说没有需要我调查的事了?
I take it there's nothing for me to investigate?
当然 安全方面没有了
Not at all. Not on security grounds.
好 那就不打扰您了
Good. I'll take up no more of your time.
等等 还有失职的问题呢
Hold on. There's still the incompetence.
当然 首相 人非圣贤 孰能无过啊
Well, of course, we all make mistakes.
这过失也太大了 你觉得我该炒他吗?
Not on that scale. Think I should sack him?
恕难同意
I hardly think so.
怎么 公务员永远不该被炒吗?
Why not? Should civil servants never be sacked?
如果他们罪有应得 当然应该
If they deserve it, of course they should
在原则上 但实践中不行
In principle, but not in practice.
怎么不行?      那就得发起调查
Why not?        There would have to be an inquiry.
一旦调查起公务员失职问题
All inquiries into the incompetence of civil servants
总会追溯到大臣犯错
somehow seem to be back to mistakes by ministers.
话说回来 还是等我决定吧
On second thoughts, leave it with me.
谢谢 首相
Thank you, Prime Minister.
汉弗莱爵士到了
Sir Humphrey is outside.
请他进来 伯纳 请他进来
Show him in, Bernard. Show him in!
首相
Prime Minister.
呆瓜 呃...汉弗莱
Goofy. Er, Humphrey.
很高兴告诉你 你的间谍嫌疑洗清了
I'm happy to tell you that you've been cleared of spying.
怎么?      约翰霍斯顿爵士的一份手稿
How?        Something Sir John Halsted wrote.
真令人欣慰
Oh, that's very gratifying.
可不是吗 就知道你会高兴
Isn't it? I knew you will be pleased.
当事人本人可否看看?
May one see the document?
当事人当然可以
One certainly may.
更好的办法 是让别人念给当事人听
Better still, one can have it read to one.
"5月28日
''May 28th.
又一次会见了那个头号呆瓜阿普比
Another session with that prize goof Appleby.
耍得他团团转"
Fooled him completely...''
明白了 谢谢 首相
Yes, I see, while thank you. Prime Minister
不不 接着听 后面洗清得更彻底
No, it goes on. It clears you even more.
"他没问半个棘手的问题
''He never asked any difficult questions.
连军情五处报告..."
didn't seem to have read the MI5 report.''
对 清楚了 多谢
Yes, that's quite clear. Thank you.
"他脑子那么迟钝
''So much wool in his head,
糊弄他纯属小菜一碟"
it's child's play to pull it over his eyes.''
多么精彩啊
Isn't that wonderful?
你一定开心极了
You must be a very happy man.
我一直说 霍斯顿不善识人
I always said Halsted was a hopeless judge of character.
你是说这不可信? 他胡扯?
You mean we can't believe this? He was lying?
不不不 不 不 这绝对是真的
Oh, no, no, no. No, no, it's absolutely true.
所谓真 我是说从...
True, that is, in the sense of...
您看 他不够聪明
You see, he wasn't bright enough
不能理解微妙的询问技巧
to understand subtle questioning techniques.
婉转探听法
The non-confrontational approach.
导致他真的平安无事?      不不不
Lulled him into a true sense of security?        No, no, no.
总之 这件事到此结束了?
Anyway, I take it it's all over now?
串通的事结束了
The matter of collusion, yes.
可要是你手下如此失职 你能原谅吗?
But would you condone incompetence of this sort?
都过去这么久了 首相
It was a long time ago. Prime Minister.
我当时压力很大 公务繁忙
I was under great stress. I had many other onerous duties.
你现在也很繁忙啊
You have many other onerous duties now.
对 说实话
Yes. And, in fact...
我一直在思考
..I have been giving some thought to how
您如何才能提高支持率       是吗?
you might increase your popularity rating.      Yes?
强健的政府需要有民望的首相      那么
Strong government needs a popular PM.        So
您应该做些受欢迎的事
What I think you should do something popular.
当然 可做什么呢?
Of course. But what?
我正要建议
What I was about to suggest
您能否亲自出面
that you might intervene personally
营救索尔兹伯里平原上可怜的小狗
to save that poor little doggie on Salisbury Plain.
汉弗莱 你说真的?      当然 首相
Humphrey. Are you serious?        Of course. Prime Minister.
这绝对会大受欢迎的
It certainly would be very popular.
成本会很高吗?      当然不会
Would it be very expensive?        Surely not.
我们能担得起吗?
Could we cost it?
依我之见 小本琪时间已经不多了
Well, I gather that time is running out for little Benji.
我们必须今天早晨下决定
We have to make a decision this morning.
人有些时候就得凭良心行事
There are times when you have to act from the heart,
首相也不例外
even as Prime Minister.
你说得对 汉弗莱      可以吗?
You're right, Humphrey!        May I?
拜托了
Please do it.
这不是收买便宜人心的问题 对吧?
It's not a question of buying a little cheap popularity, isn't it?
绝对不是
By no means.
会花很久吗?
Will it take long?
我已经吩咐军队待命三小时
I've got the Army on three-hour standby.
只等您一句话
All I need is your clearance.
太好了      是你吗 诺曼? 开工
Splendid.        Is that you, Norman? Walkies.
终于 本琪 那条走失在
And finally, Benji, the 0ld English sheepdog
索尔兹伯里平原的老英国牧羊犬
lost on the artillery range on Salisbury Plain
已被安全营救 马丁慕卡斯现场报道
has been rescued. Martin Muncaster reports.
今天午后 行动从乙区这里展开
The operation began here on B Range early this afternoon.
四队皇家工兵持探雷器
Four detachments of the Royal Engineers with mine detectors
由不同地点出发
set off from different points
向本琪最后出现的地点包抄
to close in on the area where Benji was last sighted.
他们花了一小时找到它
It took them over an hour to locate him.
然后皇家兽医用麻醉枪 让本吉暂时休克
Then the Royal Veterinary Corps fired a stun dart at Benji.
不幸的是 该区域太危险
Unfortunately, the area is too dangerous
引爆所有炸弹又可能伤及狗
to enter without detonating shells which may injure the dog,
因此皇家海军直升机开进现场
so a Royal Navy helicopter was flown in
空中抢险队放下人员救起本琪
and the air rescue team lowered a man to pick up Benji
空运至安全地带 以免穿越危险地面
without crossing the dangerous ground and fly him to safety.
之后 它回到了小主人琳达弗莱彻的怀抱
Later, he was reunited with his young owner, Linda Fletcher
她说她几乎
who said she'd almost
不敢盼望与本琪重聚了
given up hope of ever seeing Benji again.
据悉 是首相的直接干涉
It's understood that it was the direct intervention
促成了此事
from the PM which made the rescue operation possible.
亲爱的 你派他们去救狗了      对
Darling, you got them to rescue that dog!        Yes.
你说这是浪费钱的
You said it would be a waste of money.
我知道 但我考虑了你的话
I know, and I thought what you said.
政府应该关心嘛
government is caring.
关心选票?      别这么刻薄 安妮
Caring about votes?        That's not very kind, Annie.
我想到那个小女孩
I thought about that little girl
还有本琪对她的意义 个人的确有分量
and what Benji must mean to her. Individuals do count,
即使在一个预算和收支平衡表的世界里
even in a world of budgets and balance sheets.
有些人可能会批评我滥用军队
Some people might criticise me make using the army that way
可有时候 做正确的事
but sometimes doing the right thing
就得牺牲些民望
means risking unpopularity.
我可不会批评你 亲爱的 我觉得你太棒了
Well,I won't criticise you,darling.I think you're wonderful.
看到了吗 汉弗莱?
See this, Humphrey?
"英国今天明白了 还有一颗真正的人心
''Britain learned today that a real human heart
在唐宁街10号跳动"
beats inside Number 10 Downing Street.''
实际上 有74颗人心在这里跳呢
Actually, 74 human hearts beat inside NO.10 Downing Street
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard.
瞧 我说得对 我凭直觉就知道人们的需求
See? I was right. I have an instinct for what people want.
恕我直言 首相...
If I may say so, Prime Minister...
当然 是你的主意 对吗?
Of course! It was your idea, wasn't it?
干得好 我能怎么报答你呢?
Well done. What can I do for you?
霍斯顿调查?
The Halsted inquiry?
不用再提了 我彻底忘了
Say no more about it. Completely forgotten.
谢谢 首相 可以讨论内阁议程了吗?
Oh, thank you.PM. Now may we discuss the Cabinet agenda?
有一两件事
One or two points.
第3项...
Item 3...
琳达说"我投哈克先生一票"
Linda says, ''My vote goes to Mr Hacker!''
您说什么?      对不起 汉弗莱 什么?
I beg your pardon?        I'm sorry, Humphrey. Yes?
"BBC和ITV接到潮水般的电话"
''BBC and ITV report a flood of phone calls,
"人们交口称赞首相营救本琪的决定"
''all approving the PM's decision to rescue Benji.''
我能否建议我们推迟第3项 首相?
May I suggest that we postpone Item 3, Prime Minister?
"反对党领袖拒不出面评论"
'The Leader of the Opposition was not available for comment'
谅他也不敢
I bet he wasn't!
要么支持我 要么让宠物狗饿死
Support me or let pet dogs starve to death!
我真把他难住了 对吧?
I really had him there, didn't I?
抱歉 汉弗莱      第3项 首相
Sorry, Humphrey.        Item 3. Prime Minister.
对 第3项是什么? 削减军费? 怎么啦?
Item 3. Yes, what's Item 3? Defence cuts? What about them?
我建议 先提交内阁委员会讨论
I'm going to suggest we'd refer them to Cabinet Committee.
不行 我要本周四出决定
No, I want a decision on Thursday,
不要明年三月一份60页的报告
not a 60-page submission next Easter.
啊 可我刚刚收到了预估的
Ah, because I've just had the provisional costings
救狗行动成本
for the dog rescue operation.
31万英镑?
310,000?
不可能
That's impossible!
这是国防部根据实际成本计算的
Those are MOD figures on a true-cost basis.
太荒唐了 汉弗莱 得想点办法
This is absurd. We must do something.
把狗放回去?
Put the dog back?
岂有此理 反正我不延迟第3项
That's ridiculous. Anyhow I'm not postponing Item 3.
由您决定 首相
Well, it's your decision, Prime Minister.
真是有魄力的决定 容我这么说
And a very courageous one, if I may say so.
有魄力? 为什么?
Courageous? Why?
如果真的削减了军费
Well, if the defence cuts are made,
救狗的成本肯定会被漏给媒体
the cost of rescuing a dog is bound to be leaked to the press
不是吧
Oh, no.
除非您完全信任国防部的保密工作
Unless you have faith in MOD confidentiality in loyalty.
别傻了 他们漏得跟筛子一样
Don't be absurd! Of course, they leak like sieves.
结果可想而知
I can see it now.
"首相救狗 英国空军买单"
"PM saves dog at expense of Britain's air defences"
多劲爆的故事      一个落水狗的故事
It would be quite a story.        A shaggy dog story.
可消息不会泄露 除非...
But it would only come out if...
我不吃勒索这一套      当然不
I'm not going to be blackmailed.        Of course not.
话说回来 军费也不能削减过分
On the other hand, one can cut defence too far.
当然
Absolutely.
领土防卫 政府第一要务
Defence of the realm. First duty of government.
第一要务
First duty.
总有紧急情况 朝鲜 马岛
There are emergencies - Korea, the Falklands.
本琪      本琪 对
Benji.        Benji! Yes.
我想我是太急进了点
I think I may have been a little hasty.
对 第3项还需要多加考虑
Yes,I think Item 3 probably needs a bit more thought.
再明智不过了
I'm sure that's wise.
不能着急
And there is no hurry.
把削减军费的事提交委员会 好吗?
Refer defence cuts to committee, would you?
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
破烂熊字幕组-==www.RagBear.com==-